María Díaz de León Derby

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Developing engineering and machine learning tools for global health. My current research focuses on portable diagnostic tools and techniques for the diagnosis of neglected tropical diseases, a group of conditions that affect one billion of the world's most vulnerable people.

EDUCATION

Ongoing	University of California, Berkeley and University of California, San Francisco Ph.D. in Bioengineering (expected graduation December 2024) Advised by Prof. Daniel Fletcher
2013-18	Tecnológico de Monterrey, Mexico (ITESM) Bachelor of Science in Mechatronics Engineering GPA of 96/100
2016-17	Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, Germany (KIT) DAAD Mexican Engineers Exchange Programme Faculty of Mechanical Engineering
2014-15	University of British Columbia, Canada (UBC) International Student Exchange Program School of Engineering

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Ongoing University of California, Berkeley

Bioengineering department

Supervisor: Prof. Daniel Fletcher

Development of tools and techniques for portable infectious disease diagnostics:

- 1. Multi-contrast machine learning to improve schistosomiasis diagnostic performance.
- 2. NTDscope: portable microscope for diagnostics of neglected tropical diseases.
- 3. Mobile phone-based platform for COVID-19 diagnosis using CRISPR-Cas13.

2018-19 Tecnológico de Monterrey, Mexico (ITESM)

School of Engineering and Sciences

Supervisors: Prof. Mario Moises Alvarez and Prof. Grissel Trujillo de Santiago

Continuous 3D chaotic printing: developed a method to continuously fabricate complex microstructure at high resolution by using the chaotic flow induced by a Kenics static mixer.

2017 Daimler AG, Sindelfingen, Germany

Mercedes Benz Research and Development

Internship in the field of Hybrid Drives: data analysis, development and testing. Developed a MATLAB evaluation tool for analysing sensor data obtained from test vehicles.

2014-16 University of British Columbia, Canada (UBC)

School of Engineering

Supervisor: Prof. Mina Hoorfar

Development of a technique for static droplet mixing in digital microfluidics and a digital microfluidics cell-patterning system.

^{*} denotes equal contribution.

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Jean T. Coulibaly, Kigbafori D. Silue, **María Díaz de León Derby**, Daniel A. Fletcher, Karla N. Fisher, Jason R. Andrews, and Isaac I. Bogoch. "Rapid and Comprehensive Screening for Urogenital and Gastrointestinal Schistosomiasis with Handheld Digital Microscopy Combined with Circulating Cathodic Antigen Testing". In: *The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene* (June 2024).
- [2] Jean T. Coulibaly, Kigbafori D. Silue, Maxim Armstrong, María Díaz de León Derby, Michael V. D'Ambrosio, Daniel A. Fletcher, Jennifer Keiser, Karla Fisher, Jason R. Andrews, and Isaac I. Bogoch. "High Sensitivity of Mobile Phone Microscopy Screening for Schistosoma haematobium in Azaguié, Côte d'Ivoire". In: The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene 108.1 (2023), pp. 41–43.
- [3] Sita S. Chandrasekaran, Shreeya Agrawal, Alison Fanton, Aditya R. Jangid, Bérénice Charrez, Arturo M. Escajeda, Sungmin Son, Roger Mcintosh, Huyen Tran, Abdul Bhuiya, María Díaz de León Derby, et al. "Rapid detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in saliva via Cas13". In: Nature Biomedical Engineering 6.8 (Aug. 2022), pp. 944–956.
- [4] Parinaz Fozouni*, Sungmin Son*, **María Díaz de León Derby***, Gavin J. Knott, Carley N. Gray, Michael V. D'Ambrosio, Chunyu Zhao, Neil A. Switz, G. Renuka Kumar, Stephanie I. Stephens, Daniela Boehm, et al. "Amplification-free detection of SARS-CoV-2 with CRISPR-Cas13a and mobile phone microscopy". In: *Cell* 184.2 (2021), 323–333.e9.
- [5] Tina Y. Liu, Gavin J. Knott, Dylan C. J. Smock, John J. Desmarais, Sungmin Son, Abdul Bhuiya, Shrutee Jakhanwal, Noam Prywes, Shreeya Agrawal, María Díaz de León Derby, Neil A. Switz, et al. "Accelerated RNA detection using tandem CRISPR nucleases". In: Nature Chemical Biology 17.9 (Sept. 2021), pp. 982–988.
- [6] Carolina Chávez-Madero*, María Díaz de León Derby*, Mohamadmahdi Samandari, Carlos Fernando Ceballos-González, Edna Johana Bolívar-Monsalve, Christian Mendoza-Buenrostro, Sunshine Holmberg, Norma Alicia Garza-Flores, Mohammad Ali Almajhadi, Ivonne González-Gamboa, Juan Felipe Yee-de León, et al. "Using chaotic advection for facile high-throughput fabrication of ordered multilayer micro- and nanostructures: continuous chaotic printing". In: Biofabrication 12.3 (June 2020), p. 035023.
- [7] Ehsan Samiei, **María Díaz de León Derby**, Andre Van den Berg, and Mina Hoorfar. "An electrohydrodynamic technique for rapid mixing in stationary droplets on digital microfluidic platforms". In: *Lab Chip* 17 (2 2017), pp. 227–234.
- [8] B. A. Nestor, E. Samiei, R. Samanipour, A. Gupta, A. Van den Berg, María Díaz de León Derby, Z. Wang, H. Rezaei Nejad, K. Kim, and M. Hoorfar. "Digital microfluidic platform for dielectrophoretic patterning of cells encapsulated in hydrogel droplets". In: RSC Adv. 6 (62 2016), pp. 57409–57416.

PATENTS

[1] Grissel Trujillo De Santiago, Mario Moisés Álvarez, Carlos Fernando Ceballos González, Edna Johana Bolívar Monsalve, **María Díaz de León Derby**, Carolina Chávez Madero, Daniele Tammaro, and Ernesto Di Maio. "Method for printing microlayers and multilayered nanostructures ordered by chaotic flows". WO2022229721A1. Nov. 2022.

Presentations

- 10/2023 American Society for Tropical Medicine and Hygiene 2023 Annual Meeting
 Poster: Multi-Contrast and Multi-Modal Machine Learning to Automate Schistosoma haematobium Diagnostics at the Point-Of-Care
- 03/2023 Tropical Infectious Diseases Gordon Research Seminar
 Poster and Talk: Mobile Phone-based Diagnostics for Neglected Tropical Diseases: Automated
 Identification of Schistosoma haematobium from Urine Samples
- 10/2022 American Society for Tropical Medicine and Hygiene 2022 Annual Meeting: Advances in Point-Of-Care Technologies for NTDs Symposium Talk: Machine Learning for Automated Schistosomiasis Detection

10/2022	UC Berkeley/UCSF Graduate Program in Bioengineering: Annual Conference and Retreat Talk: Mobile Phone-based Diagnostics for Neglected Tropical Diseases
05/2022	Measuring Development 2022: The Role of Mobile Data in Global Development Talk: Mobile Phone-based Diagnostics for Neglected Tropical Diseases
09/2021	UC Berkeley Health Tech Co-Lab Grand Opening Invited Talk: Harnessing Mobile Phones for Diagnosis of Neglected Tropical Diseases
05/2021	Conversations on Bioinspired Engineering - Seminar Series, UC Berkeley Invited Talk: Amplification-free detection of SARS-CoV-2 with CRISPR-Cas13a and mobile phone microscopy
08/2018	ACS Fall 2018 National Meeting and Exposition Poster: Continuous 3D chaotic printing: Using the chaotic flow induced by a Kenics mixer to continuously fabricate complex micro- and/or nanostructure at high resolution
01/2018	2018 Research and Development Congress at ITESM Poster: Continuous 3D chaotic printing: Using the chaotic flow induced by a Kenics mixer to continuously fabricate complex microstructure at high resolution

TEACHING AND MENTORING

2023 Graduate Student Mentor, Berkeley Bioegineering Scholars Program

- Mentored one Bioengineering undergraduate student to design a gravity-assisted syringe pump to facilitate sample preparation for point-of-care diagnostics of Schistosomiasis.

2022 Teaching Assistant, Marine Biological Laboratory: Physiology Course

- Mentored a graduate student on a research project investigating the immune-evasion properties of eggs of *Schistosoma* parasites.

2021 Graduate Student Instructor, University of California, Berkeley

- Course: Bioengineering 168L Practical Light Microscopy
- Lead Instructor: Prof. Daniel Fletcher
- Led a laboratory section, conducted weekly office hours, and graded assignments.

2019-21 Teaching Assistant, Center for Cellular Construction Workshop

- Helped design and teach a series of two week workshops where 20 high school students and teachers were introduced to cellular engineering and programmed robots that mimic cellular behaviour.

SERVICE

2018-20 Diversity, Equity and Inclusion (DEI) Enhancement Committee, UC Berkeley-UCSF Bioengineering Association of Students (BEAST)

- Founding Member with five other PhD students
- Organized and led a DEI workshop for our student body at the annual retreat
- Recruited prospective students at 2019 SACNAS National Diversity in STEM Conference
- Worked with the BioE Executive and Admissions Committees to increase the diversity of our program's incoming cohort of students
- Evaluated candidates in department faculty searches for contributions to DEI

2020 Visit Weekend Committee Co-Chair, UC Berkeley-UCSF Bioengineering

- Led the committee of students in charge of the two recruitment visits of the year, where more than 80 prospective students visited our program

AWARDS AND DISTINCTIONS

2022	SACNAS National Diversity in STEM Conference Student Travel Award
2021	UC Berkeley/UCSF Bioengineering Service and DEIB Award
2020	Craven Award in Bioengineering (UC Berkeley Bioengineering)
2019	UC MEXUS-CONACYT Doctoral Fellowship
2016	Mitacs Globalink Fellowship
2016	DAAD Mexican Engineers Scholarship
2014	Emerging Leaders in the Americas Program Scholarship

VOLUNTEER WORK

2021-22	Dia de la Ingeneria/Latinx Engineering Day at the Exploratorium Museum
	Led the bilingual exhibit "Exploración con microscopios basados en teléfonos celulares".
2022	Be A Scientist
	Graduate student mentor at Longfellow Middle School in Berkeley, California. Mentored 3

middle school students as they designed and executed science experiments.

2014-16 **Prepanet**Science and Mathematics tutor for an online high school system serving underprivileged Mexican students.

2013-16 Team LamBot 3478 (FIRST Robotics Competition)
Head coach responsible for leading a group of 15 academic and industry mentors and 50 high school students from San Luis Potosí, Mexico.

2013-14 FIRST Robotics Competition
Judge assistant, field assembly volunteer, and referee.

LANGUAGES

Spanish Native
English Native
German Very Good Comm

German Very Good Command (B2.2)

French Intermediate